<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with your Android tablet</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started-with-your-android-tablet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getting-started-with-your-android-tablet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Mobile devices such as mobile phones and tablets have become valuable tools in data collection. Various applications have been and are being developed specifically to harness the utility of mobile devices for collecting data. An understanding of how mobile devices work specifically those powered by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.android.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Android operating system&lt;/a&gt; is therefore a requisite knowledge for anyone involved in a data collection campaign that utilises these devices for data collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial gives a brief overview on how to get started with an Android device. We chose to focus on the use of tablet devices because we think that the smaller sized tablets (up to 7-inch) are a good mix of the mobility and handiness of a mobile phone and the wider screen size of a tablet which is good for fitting relatively dense question sets adequately. We also chose to focus on Samsung-branded because they are probably the most common brand of mobile devices available and we think most users have most likely had an experience using devices from this brand beforehand. For this specific tutorial, we use the &lt;strong&gt;Samsung SM-T230&lt;/strong&gt; as the model device for instructional purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial is aimed at enumerators who may have not been exposed to smartphones particularly Android-powered devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-device-layout&#34;&gt;1. Device layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front layout of the &lt;strong&gt;Samsung SM-T230&lt;/strong&gt; is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/tabletFront.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The back layout looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/tabletBack.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;buttons&#34;&gt;Buttons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press and hold to turn the device on or off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press and hold for 8 seconds to reset the device if it has fatal errors or hang-ups, or freezes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press to lock the device. The device goes into lock mode when the touch screen turns off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent apps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tap to open the list of recent applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Home&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press to return to the Home Screen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press and hold to launch Google search.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tap to return to the previous screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volume&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press to adjust the device volume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-charging-the-battery&#34;&gt;2. Charging the battery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before using the device for the first time or when the battery has been unused for extended periods, you must charge the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connect the USB cable to the USB power adaptor and then plug the end of the USB cable into the multipurpose jack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/samsungConnectPC.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The device can be used while it is charging, but it may take longer to fully charge the battery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the device receives an unstable power supply while charging, the touch screen may not function. If this happens, unplug the charger from the device.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While charging, the device may heat up. This is normal and should not affect the device&amp;rsquo;s lifespan or performance. If the battery gets hotter than usual, the charger may stop charging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After fully charging, disconnect the device from the charger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your device provides options that help you save the battery power. By customising these options and deactivating features in the background, you can use the device longer between charges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you are not using the device, switch to sleep mode by pressing the Power button.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Close unnecessary applications with the task manager.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deactivate the Bluetooth feature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deactivate the WiFi feature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deactivate auto-syncing of applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decrease the backlight time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decrease the brightness of the display.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-turning-the-device-on-and-off&#34;&gt;3. Turning the device on and off&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When turning on the device for the first time, follow the on-screen instructions to setup your device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press and hold the Power button for a few seconds to turn on the device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/tabletOff.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To turn off the device, press and hold the Power button, and then tap &lt;strong&gt;Power off&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-locking-and-unlocking-the-device&#34;&gt;4. Locking and unlocking the device&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When not in use, lock the device to prevent unwanted operation. Pressing the Power button turns off the screen and puts the device into lock mode. The device automatically gets locked if it is not used for a specified period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To unlock the device, press the Power button or Home button when the touch screen is turned off, tap anywhere on the screen, and then flick your finger in any direction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing ODK Collect without using Google Play Store - Approach 1</title>
      <link>/post/installing-odk-collect-without-using-google-play-store-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/installing-odk-collect-without-using-google-play-store-1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There are situations in which access to the &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; might be limited for a variety reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may not have a &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt; which is required to be able to access the &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There may be region or country-specific limitations to accessing either your &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; or both; or,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is simply no internet connectivity in the area you are located in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such situations would limit your ability to install applications including &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a problem when the mobile devices you are going to use for your data collection are not yet configured and &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; not yet installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial addresses the problem described in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;situation 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; above where access to &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt; and/or &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; is limited but access to internet is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;situation 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, steps 2 to 4 of this tutorial will still apply but it would require that you have already done step 1 ahead of time where access to internet is available which will allow you to download a copy of the application to be installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial shows how to install &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; without using &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; (and without requiring a &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt;). Instead, the &lt;strong&gt;Open Data Kit&lt;/strong&gt; application package is downloaded onto a computer and then transferred to the tablet for installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process requires a computer and a USB to micro-USB cable to connect the tablet to the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-download-open-data-kit-apk&#34;&gt;1. Download Open Data Kit APK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First you need to download the &lt;strong&gt;Open Data Kit APK&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;APK&lt;/strong&gt; is short for Android application package which is the package file format used by the Android operating system for distribution and installation of mobile apps. Here are the steps to download the &lt;strong&gt;Open Data Kit APK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-1-go-to-the-open-data-kit-website&#34;&gt;1.1 Go to the Open Data Kit website&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On your web browser, type in &lt;a href=&#34;https://opendatakit.org.&#34;&gt;https://opendatakit.org.&lt;/a&gt; You will then see the following webpage on your browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/go-to-the-open-data-kit-website.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-2-go-to-the-download-page&#34;&gt;1.2 Go to the Download page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of the webpage, you will see the menu of the website one of which is named &amp;lt;em &lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;Download&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Download&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/go-to-the-download-page.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-3-select-the-odk-collect-apk-from-the-download-list&#34;&gt;1.3 Select the ODK Collect APK from the download list&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are at the Download page, you will see a list of the various downloads that are available from the Open Data Kit site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; as item number 3 in the Collect section of the Download page &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have found the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt;, click on the link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/select-the-odk-collect-apk-from-the-download-list-1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-4-click-download&#34;&gt;1.4 Click Download&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/click-download.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-5-find-the-downloaded-odk-collect-apk&#34;&gt;1.5 Find the downloaded ODK Collect APK&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, all downloads are saved in the computer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder. Navigate to your computer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder to see that the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; has been downloaded successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/find-the-downloaded-odk-collect-apk.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-6-move-odk-collect-apk-to-your-desktop&#34;&gt;1.6 Move ODK Collect APK to your Desktop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step is not absolutely necessary but it will make things easier in terms of the next steps because it will make it easier for you to locate the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; file. Drag the ODK Collect APK file from the &lt;strong&gt;Downloads&lt;/strong&gt; folder onto your &lt;strong&gt;Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/move-odk-collect-apk-to-your-desktop.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-6-move-odk-collect-apk-to-your-desktop-1&#34;&gt;1.6 Move ODK Collect APK to your Desktop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now see the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; on your &lt;strong&gt;Desktop&lt;/strong&gt; making it easier to access later for the next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/16-move-odk-collect-apk-to-your-desktop.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-transfer-the-odk-collect-apk-to-your-tablet&#34;&gt;2. Transfer the ODK Collect APK to your tablet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now need to transfer the ODK Collect APK to your tablet. This can be done by following these steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-1-connect-your-tablet-to-your-computer&#34;&gt;2.1 Connect your tablet to your computer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the the USB to Micro-USB cable supplied with your tablet, connect the tablet to your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/samsungConnectPC-1024x654.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-2-navigate-to-the-directory-of-your-tablet&#34;&gt;2.2 Navigate to the directory of your tablet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, tablets are configured in such a way that when they are connected to a computer, they function as a USB mass-storage device (just like a USB memory stick). This means that when you connect to a computer, the tablet will appear on the computer as another storage device with its own directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to be able to navigate to the directory of your tablet, open &lt;strong&gt;Windows Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; and you should find your tablet (if you have named your tablet, you will see the name of the tablet) listed as a storage device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/navigate-to-the-directory-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you click on the name of your tablet, a sub-directory called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Tablet&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; will appear and then you will now see the contents of your tablet organised in folders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/22-navigate-to-the-directory-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-3-find-and-open-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet&#34;&gt;2.3 Find and open the Download folder of your tablet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the Download folder of your tablet by double-clicking on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/find-and-open-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder will contain all downloads that you have made on your tablet. In this case, there are no downloads yet on the tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/23-find-and-open-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-4-transfer-the-odk-collect-apk-from-your-computer-to-the-tablet-s-download-folder&#34;&gt;2.4 Transfer the ODK Collect APK from your computer to the tablet&amp;rsquo;s Download folder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, you have placed the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; to the desktop which makes it more accessible to you for transferring into the tablets &lt;strong&gt;Donwload&lt;/strong&gt; folder. Select the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; on your &lt;strong&gt;Desktop&lt;/strong&gt; and then drag and drop it to copy into your tablet&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/transfer-the-odk-collect-apk-from-your-computer-to-the-tablet-s-download-folder.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now see the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/24-transfer-the-odk-collect-apk-from-your-computer-to-the-tablet-s-download-folder.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store&#34;&gt;3. Set-up tablet device to allow installation of applications outside of the Google Play Store&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now need to set-up your tablet device to allow installation of application outside of Google Play Store. Following are the steps you need to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-1-go-to-security-settings-of-your-tablet&#34;&gt;3.1 Go to Security settings of your tablet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your tablet device, open the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Settings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; application, then navigate to the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;General&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; tab &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp;and then the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; settings &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt;. You will now see the various &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; settings. For this step, you wll need to focus on the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Device Administration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; section specifically the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unknown sources&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; option &lt;strong&gt;(3)&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the option that will allow you to install applications from other sources other than the Google Play Store. By default, this option is not checked. Check this option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/go-to-security-settings-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-1-nbsp-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store&#34;&gt;3.1 &amp;nbsp; Set-up tablet device to allow installation of applications outside of the Google Play Store&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you check this option, you will get a warning regarding installint application from unknown sources. Tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;OK&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/31-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The option to install from unknown sources is now checked &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. You can now continue with the next steps for installing &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/31-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store-1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-install-odk-collect-on-your-tablet&#34;&gt;4. Install ODK Collect on your tablet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you need to install &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet using the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; that you just transferred to your tablet. This can be done by following these steps.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-1-navigate-to-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet&#34;&gt;4.1 Navigate to the Download folder of your tablet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this step, you will need a file manager application to be able to navigate the contents of your tablet. For some devices such as those from the Samsung line of mobile devices, there is a pre-installed file manager application called &amp;lsquo;My Files&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/navigate-to-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;My Files&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; file manager application and then click on ***&amp;lsquo;Device Storage&amp;rsquo; ***&lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. You will now see all the folders inside the tablet including the &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt;. Open the &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/41-navigate-to-download-folder-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now see the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; which you have transferred earlier from your computer &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. You can now proceed with installing the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/41-navigate-to-download-folder-on-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-2-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk&#34;&gt;4.2 Tap on the ODK Collect APK&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have found the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; on the &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder of your tablet, tap the APK to initiate installation. You will now see the following prompt on your tablet screen. Tap &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Next&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next screen will look like this. Tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Intsall&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/42-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next screen will indicate that ODK Collect is now installing on your tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/42-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk-1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see this screen on your tablet to indicate the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; has been installed. You can tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Open&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to start using &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/42-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk-2.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-3-start-using-odk-collect&#34;&gt;4.3 Start using ODK Collect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now start using &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/start-using-odk-collect.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing ODK Collect without using Google Play Store - Approach 2</title>
      <link>/post/installing-odk-collect-without-using-google-play-store-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/installing-odk-collect-without-using-google-play-store-2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There are situations in which access to the &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; might be limited for a variety reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may not have a &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt; which is required to be able to access the &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There may be region or country-specific limitations to accessing either your &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; or both; or,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is simply no internet connectivity in the area you are located in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such situations would limit your ability to install applications including &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a problem when the mobile devices you are going to use for your data collection are not yet configured and &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; not yet installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial addresses the problem described in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;situation 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; above where access to &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt; and/or &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; is limited but access to internet is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;situation 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, steps 2 and 3 of this tutorial will still apply but it would require that you have already done step 1 ahead of time where access to internet is available which will allow you to download a copy of the application on your tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial shows how to install &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; without using &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt; (and without requiring a &lt;strong&gt;Google account&lt;/strong&gt;). Instead, the &lt;strong&gt;Open Data Kit&lt;/strong&gt; application package is downloaded direct onto your tablet and then installed directly without going through &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-download-open-data-kit-apk&#34;&gt;1. Download Open Data Kit APK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First you need to download the &lt;strong&gt;Open Data Kit APK&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet. &lt;strong&gt;APK&lt;/strong&gt; is short for Android application package which is the package file format used by the Android operating system for distribution and installation of mobile apps. Here are the steps to download the &lt;strong&gt;Open Data Kit APK&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-1-go-to-the-open-data-kit-website&#34;&gt;1.1 Go to the Open Data Kit website&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the web browser in your tablet, type in &lt;a href=&#34;https://opendatakit.org.&#34;&gt;https://opendatakit.org.&lt;/a&gt; You will then see the following webpage on your tablet&amp;rsquo;s browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/Screenshot_2016-02-11-08-14-00-640x1024.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-2-go-to-the-download-page&#34;&gt;1.2 Go to the Download page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of the webpage, you will see the menu of the website one of which is named &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Download&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Download&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/go-to-the-download-page-1-1-640x1024.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-3-select-the-odk-collect-apk-from-the-download-list&#34;&gt;1.3 Select the ODK Collect APK from the download list&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are at the Download page, you will see a list of the various downloads that are available from the Open Data Kit site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; as item number 3 in the Collect section of the Download page &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have found the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt;, tap on the link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/select-the-odk-collect-apk-from-the-download-list-1-1-640x1024.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-4-tap-download&#34;&gt;1.4 Tap Download&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/tap-download-640x1024.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store&#34;&gt;2. Set-up tablet device to allow installation of applications outside of the Google Play Store&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now need to set-up your tablet device to allow installation of application outside of &lt;strong&gt;Google Play Store&lt;/strong&gt;. Following are the steps you need to take.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-1-go-to-security-settings-of-your-tablet&#34;&gt;2.1 Go to Security settings of your tablet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your tablet device, open the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Settings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; application, then navigate to the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;General&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; tab &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp;and then the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; settings &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt;. You will now see the various &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Security&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; settings. For this step, you wll need to focus on the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Device Administration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; section specifically the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unknown sources&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; option &lt;strong&gt;(3)&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the option that will allow you to install applications from other sources other than the Google Play Store. By default, this option is not checked. Check this option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/go-to-security-settings-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-2-nbsp-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store&#34;&gt;2.2 &amp;nbsp; Set-up tablet device to allow installation of applications outside of the Google Play Store&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you check this option, you will get a warning regarding installint application from unknown sources. Tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;OK&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to continue.
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/31-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The option to install from unknown sources is now checked &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. You can now continue with the next steps for installing &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/31-set-up-tablet-device-to-allow-installation-of-applications-outside-of-the-google-play-store-1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-install-odk-collect-on-your-tablet&#34;&gt;3. Install ODK Collect on your tablet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you need to install &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet using the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; that you just transferred to your tablet. This can be done by following these steps.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-1-navigate-to-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet&#34;&gt;3.1 Navigate to the Download folder of your tablet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this step, you will need a file manager application to be able to navigate the contents of your tablet. For some devices such as those from the Samsung line of mobile devices, there is a pre-installed file manager application called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;My Files&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/navigate-to-the-download-folder-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;My Files&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; file manager application and then click on ***&amp;lsquo;Device Storage&amp;rsquo; ***&lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. You will now see all the folders inside the tablet including the &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt;. Open the &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/41-navigate-to-download-folder-of-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now see the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; which you have transferred earlier from your computer &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. You can now proceed with installing the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/41-navigate-to-download-folder-on-your-tablet.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-2-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk&#34;&gt;3.2 Tap on the ODK Collect APK&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have found the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect APK&lt;/strong&gt; on the &lt;strong&gt;Download&lt;/strong&gt; folder of your tablet, tap the APK to initiate installation. You will now see the following prompt on your tablet screen. Tap &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Next&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next screen will look like this. Tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Intsall&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/42-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next screen will indicate that ODK Collect is now installing on your tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/42-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk-1.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see this screen on your tablet to indicate the &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; has been installed. You can tap on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Open&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to start using &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt; on your tablet device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/42-tap-on-the-odk-collect-apk-2.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-3-start-using-odk-collect&#34;&gt;3.3 Start using ODK Collect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can now start using &lt;strong&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/tutorials/start-using-odk-collect.png&#34; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Papua New Guinea</title>
      <link>/project/papua-new-guinea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/papua-new-guinea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Person Re-Identification System For Mobile Devices</title>
      <link>/publication/person-re-identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/person-re-identification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile visual clothing search</title>
      <link>/publication/clothing-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/clothing-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
